Finding Aid for Fred Dustin Papers 1884-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fred Dustin papers 1884-1975
Dustin, Fred, 1866-
Fred Dustin was a Saginaw, Michigan, building contractor, deputy state oil inspector, 1903-1905, and archaeological surveyor and writer on Michigan archaeology and history. The papers include correspondence, newspaper clippings, sketches, diaries, and record books concerning his interest in the archaeology of Michigan, including the archaeological survey of Isle Royale, 1929-1930, and the survey and mapping of the Ogemaw County Earthworks in 1931; also material relating to the history of Saginaw and to Dustin's interest in the archaeology of the Michigan Indian; and photographs. Correspondents include Wilber M. Brucker, Fred L. Crawford, Woodbridge N. Ferris, William B. Mershon, William A. Smith, Albert W. Tausend, Charles E. Townsend, Arthur J. Tuttle, Arthur H. Vandenberg, and Murray D. Van Wagoner.
851146 AC Aa 2
4.5 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were received in several accessions (donor no. 1771 and 3199 ).
The collection is open for research.
Fred Dustin was born Frederick Greene O'Donnell on October 12, 1866, in Glens Falls, New York. After his mother died while he was still an infant, he was raised by his aunt and uncle, Sarah and Ira Dustin, and took their last name. He attended school through the eighth grade, then began working, taking jobs in sawmills and lumberyards.
In 1887, Dustin moved to Saginaw, Michigan. After several years working in various jobs in the lumber industry, Dustin started his own carpentry business in 1890, building small items such as a hand washing machine called the Florin Washer. This business lasted until about 1900. From then on, Dustin tried his hand at a number of different types of employment, including stints as a census taker, mail carrier, weigh boss at a coal mine, building contractor, deputy state oil inspector, employment manager for a shipping plant, and Masonic Temple custodian. In his later years he ran a small bookshop out of his home and authored a book on General George Custer The Custer Tragedy, that was published in 1939. Health problems made regular employment difficult, but Dustin remained active most of his life.
Dustin had a great interest in the archaeology of Michigan. He began collecting Native American artifacts around 1903 and continued for the rest of his life, amassing over 10,000 pieces. Most of his collection was eventually donated to the University of Michigan's Museum of Anthropology. In 1929, he was appointed by the university to make an archaeological survey of Isle Royale; the work lasted about seven weeks, followed up with a four-week return visit in 1930. In 1931, the Cranbrook Institute hired Dustin to survey the prehistoric earthworks in Ogemaw County, Michigan. He also served as W.B. Hinsdale's assistant in the compilation of the Archaeological Atlas of Michigan, published in 1931.
Dustin was a charter member of the Michigan Archaeological Society and served a term as its vice president. He also published a number of articles on Saginaw archaeology and history in local newspapers in the hopes of generating interest in establishing a historical museum. In 1955, the Regents of the University of Michigan conferred a Citation of Honor upon Dustin for his contributions to the archaeology and history of the state.
Dustin married Mary Stoker in 1888. Dustin died on May 15, 1957, in Saginaw, Michigan.
The Fred Dustin Papers contain correspondence, diaries, record books, writings, field notes, photographs, and other materials that document Dustin's life and interests in Michigan archaeology and history. The papers consist of seven series: Autobiographical and Biographical, Correspondence, Archaeology, Papers and Miscellaneous, Diaries, Record Books and Ledgers, and Photographs and Scrapbook.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Dustin, Fred, 1866-; Custer, George Armstrong, 1839-1876.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Isle Royale (Mich.); Lumbering--Michigan.; Ogemaw County (Mich.); Saginaw (Mich.); Saginaw County (Mich.); Logging--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Business enterprises--Michigan--Saginaw.; Dustin, Fred, 1866-; Dwellings--Michigan--Saginaw.; Living rooms.; Photographs.; Saginaw (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Saginaw (Mich.)--Dwellings.
Contributors:
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Mershon, Wm. B. (William Butts), 1856-1943.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Tausend, Albert William, 1873-; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Genre/Form:
Diaries.
- Autobiographical and Biographical Material
  The Autobiographical and Biographical series, 1944-1975 (1 folder), contains autobiographical accounts of Dustin's life and biographical information provided by others.
  - General 1944-1975 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, 1886-1957 and undated (1.75 linear feet), contains Dustin's incoming and outgoing correspondence. The series is arranged chronologically, with one folder of undated correspondence at the front. Correspondents include Wilber M. Brucker, Fred L. Crawford, Woodbridge N. Ferris, William B. Mershon, William A. Smith, Albert W. Tausend, Charles E. Townsend, Arthur J. Tuttle, Arthur H. Vandenberg, and Murray D. Van Wagoner (an index for these correspondents is listed at the end of this finding aid).
  - undated 1886-December 1934, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - January 1935-1957, 23 folders (Box 2)
- Archaeology
  The Archaeology series, 1915-1956 and undated (0.5 linear feet), contains manuscripts, field notes, artifact lists and miscellaneous material related to Dustin's interest in the archaeology of Michigan. Of particular note are collections of manuscripts and notes related to Isle Royale and Saginaw, as well as sketches from Dustin's survey of the Ogemaw Earthworks. The series also includes field notes and manuscripts that were to be microfilmed as part of a Michigan Archaeological Society project.
  - Indian relic collections 1919-1934 (Box 2)
  - Isle Royale 1929-1941, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Archaeological Society Microfilm Project papers 1898-1957 (Box 3)
  - Notes 1920s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Papers 1915-1954, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Saginaw archaeology undated (Box 3)
  - Sketches of the Ogemaw Earthworks and Saginaw sites circa 1931-1934 (Box 3)
  - The Totem Pole, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1956, undated (Box 3)
- Papers and Miscellaneous
  The Papers and Miscellaneous series, 1886-1960 and undated (1 linear foot), is comprised of Dustin's writings on various historical, social and personal topics, as well as clippings and ephemera related to his areas of interest. Miscellaneous materials are held in chronologically arranged folders, while individual items of note are arranged alphabetically. Miscellaneous items include historical articles and book lists from Dustin's bookshop. Individual items of particular interest include a three-part history of Saginaw, Michigan, and several versions of autobiographical works on Dustin's childhood.
  - undated 1886-1960, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - Clippings on miscellaneous topics 1891-1960 (Box 3)
  - History of Saginaw 1949
    - Parts I and II, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Part III (Box 4)
  - Notes and clippings concerning Saginaw, Michigan 1895-1950 (Box 4)
  - Recollections of Boyhood
    - Rough draft 1936 (Box 4)
    - Final copy 1936 (Box 4)
  - Recollections of Youth and Young Manhood circa 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - Travels in Michigan 1913-1953 (Box 4)
- Diaries
  The Diaries series, 1884-1948 (0.25 linear feet), contains Dustin's personal diaries, which detail his activities, interests, and reflections for the dates indicated. The entries range from brief descriptions of the weather on a particular day to fuller accounts of Dustin's thoughts and plans.
  - 1884 (Box 4)
  - 1902 (Box 4)
  - circa 1917 (Box 4)
  - 1921 (Box 4)
  - 1923 (Box 4)
  - 1937-1943 (Box 4)
  - 1943-1950 (Box 4)
  - 1945-1948 (Box 4)
- Record Books and Ledgers
  The volumes in the Record Books and Ledgers series, 1887-1910 (0.5 linear feet), include Dustin's notations of financial and business transactions, but also contain his personal reflections on various topics, along with clippings and mementos.
  - 1887 (Box 4)
  - 1900-1905 (Box 4)
  - 1905-1941 (Box 4)
  - 1903 (Box 5)
    (concerning oil inspection)
  - Business account and cash books 1892-1910, 5 volumes (Box 5)
- Photographs and Scrapbook, 1890s-1950s
  The Photographs and Scrapbook series, 1890s-1950s (0.25 linear feet), consists of one envelope of photographs and a scrapbook. The photographs include portraits and candid photos of Dustin, and photos of a storefront and the interior of a Saginaw home. The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings related to Isle Royale.
  - Photographs 1890s-1950s (Box 5)
  - Isle Royale scrapbook 1928-1953 (Volume 1)
Index of Selected Correspondents
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968
1930-1932, 1935-1936, Nov. 21, 1939, Nov. 19, 1940, Nov. 21, 1946, Nov. 26, 1946, Nov. 17, 1948
Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957
Jan. 20, 1946, Jan. 30, 1946, Feb. 7, 1947, Feb. 12, 1947
Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928
Jan. 11, 1924
Mershon, William Butts, 1856-1943
Nov. 25, 1919, Jan. 8, 1924
Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932
Jan. 18, 1911, Dec. 27, 1911, Jan. 11, 1912, July 12, 1912, July 22, 1912
Tausend, Albert William, 1873-
Jan. 25, 1929, May 20, 1930
Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924
Oct. 15, 1913, Oct. 18, 1913, Nov. 3, 1913, Jan. 4, 1914, Apr. 6, 1915, Apr. 19, 1915, Sept. 7, 1921
Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944
Aug. 12, 1936, Aug. 17, 1936
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951
May 9, 1930, May 12, 1930, Feb. 14, 1936, Feb. 17, 1936, Mar. 13, 1937, Jan. 6, 1938, Jan. 10, 1938, May 20, 1939, May 22, 1939, Feb. 19, 1940
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Sept. 16, 1941